### Contact

rfvaranda@hotmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/rafaelvaranda (LinkedIn)

### Top Skills

SQL Tuning Data Modeling

**Databases** 

### Languages

Portuguese (Native or Bilingual) English (Native or Bilingual) Spanish (Elementary)

### Certifications

IBM Certified Advanced Database Administrator - DB2 9 for Linux UNIX and Windows

Big Data Foundations - Level 1
Big Data Foundations - Level 2
Hadoop Administration - Level 1
IBM Certified Database
Administrator - DB2 10.1 for Linux
UNIX and Windows

### Honors-Awards

IBM Manager's Choice Award IBM Manager's Choice Award IBM Manager's Choice Award

# Rafael Varanda

functions using SQL, PL/SQL and T-SQL.

Senior Big Data Engineer - Hadoop - AWS at Cortex Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

## Summary

Big Data Engineer with experience in Hadoop, Hive, Hbase, Map Reduce, Yarn, Ranger, Ambari, Sqoop and Python. Working as a Database Administrator for more than 19 years in Teradata, DB2, Oracle and SQL Server. Extensive experience in creating objects such as stored procedures, views, triggers and

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

- IBM Level 2 Certified IT Specialist (Open Group Certified IT Specialist)
- IBM Certified Database Associate DB2 UDB V8.1 Family
- IBM Certified Database Administrator DB2 UDB V8.1 Linux, UNIX and Windows
- IBM Certified Advanced Database Administrator DB2 UDB V8.1 Linux, UNIX and Windows
- IBM Certified Database Associate DB2 9 Fundamentals
- IBM Certified Database Administrator DB2 9 for Linux, UNIX and Windows
- IBM Certified Advanced Database Administrator DB2 9 for Linux UNIX and Windows
- IBM Certified Database Administrator DB2 9.7 for Linux, Unix and Windows
- IBM Certified Database Associate DB2 10.1 for Linux, Unix and Windows
- IBM Certified Database Administrator DB2 10.1 for Linux, Unix and Windows
- Big Data Foundations Level 1 and Level 2
- Hadoop Foundations Level 1
- Hadoop Data Access Level 1
- Hadoop Administration Level 1
- Spark Level 1
- HDP Overview: Apache Hadoop Essentials

## Experience

Cortex
Senior Big Data Engineer - Hadoop - AWS
December 2019 - Present

Rio de Janeiro e Região, Brasil

PSBI Consultoria Senior Big Data Engineer - Hadoop November 2018 - Present Rio de Janeiro e Região, Brasil

Client : Ipiranga Petróleo

Working as an independent consultant. Tasks performed in this period:
Assessment of the entire Big Data environment, aiming to show the improvements that could be implemented. Daily monitoring and maintenance of the Hadoop cluster, creation of the interfaces between Big Data and legacy Systems. Creation and maintenance of data extraction jobs using Sqoop, creation and maintenance of Hive tables. Creation of data transformation jobs using Python. Creation of jobs to read Json files using shell script.

### Indra

Senior Big Data Engineer - Hadoop October 2019 - December 2019 (3 months)

Rio de Janeiro e Região, Brasil

Client: Oi

Tasks performed in this period: Creation and maintenance of data ingestion jobs using Python and Spark, creation and maintenance of Hive tables.

### Wipro Limited

Performance Consultant - Banking, Financial Services & Insurance August 2018 - June 2019 (11 months)

Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro

Client: Bradesco Seguros

Member of the application performance team. Tasks performed in this period: Database optimization for DB2, Oracle and SQL Server, using HP-A, PCCOM, TSO, Omegamon, Freeze Frame, SQL Developer, QMF tools and DB2 Query Monitor.

### Teradata

Professional Services Consultant - Teradata - Big Data - Hadoop

Page 2 of 5

January 2018 - August 2018 (8 months)

Brasília e Região, Brasil

Client : Ministério do Desenvolvimento Social - MDS

Responsible for MDS databases. Responsible for the components installation support for the Teradata and Hadoop appliance. Big Data Consultant responsible for Hadoop, Hive, Hbase, Map Reduce, Yarn, Ranger and Ambari support. Creation and maintenance of data extraction jobs using Sqoop, creation and maintenance of Hive tables. Teradata and Hadoop integration using Teradata QueryGrid. Daily monitoring and maintenance of the Hadoop cluster.

#### **TIVIT**

Senior Database Administrator - Senior Performance Expert October 2016 - January 2018 (1 year 4 months)

Rio de Janeiro

Client: Bradesco Seguros

Member of the application performance team. Tasks performed in this period: Database optimization for DB2, Oracle and SQL Server, using HPA, PCCOM, TSO, Omegamon, Freeze Frame, SQL Developer and QMF tools. Generation of proposals for queries improvement showing the actual access plan and the optimized one, highlighting the total performance gain. Generation of monthly reports for CPU and ELAP gains.

### **IBM**

DB2 DBA - IBM Certified IT Specialist Level 2 July 2005 - March 2016 (10 years 9 months) Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

Project DeveloperWorks

Responsible for the development and production environments databases. Tasks performed in this period: DB2 installation, configuration and migration on AIX servers, applying fix packs. On call support 24x7 in production environment, creating the on call schedule rotation and working as technical leader of the DBA team. Daily verification of log files and maintenance routines, creating scripts for load routines and data refresh, data cleansing and logs.

### Project COATS / OMCS

Responsible for the test and production support environments databases.

Tasks performed in this period: DB2 installation, configuration and migration on AIX servers, applying fix packs. Configuration and maintenance of the

data replication from the MVS environment to AIX in test and production using Q Replication . Users creation and maintenance, creating scripts for daily maintenance routines.

Project ITSAS

Responsible for the test and production environments databases. Tasks performed in this period: daily verification of log files and maintenance routines, redirected restore from production databases to testing, support the data replication by adding new tables, implementation of access plans and user management and privileges.

Project IGF – Information Warehouse

Responsible for the development of the new IW interfaces. Tasks performed in this period: coordinated the meetings with the Latin America focal points for IGF applications, working with them to identify all the data to send to IW. Setup all the connections to source database using federated databases objects, creating wrapper, server definition, user mappings and nicknames. Developed the stored procedure to extract the data from the source database and generate the text file. Created the shell scripts and the bat files to call the procedure and send the file using FTP to IW server. Also created all the documentation to setup the production environment.

Xerox

Oracle DBA

January 2002 - July 2005 (3 years 7 months)

Client: Embratel

Responsible for the development and homologation databases in the Fastnet project . Functions : data modeling ,database creation for new systems , day-to-day database maintenance, stored procedures and functions tuning , jobs creation , data migration between servers , data load using Sql Loader , users creation and maintenance , creation of tables , triggers , stored procedures , functions ,views and indexes, creation of backup procedures and help the developers to resolve database problems.

Client: CSN

Creation of hot and cold backup procedures and help the developers to resolve database problems.

Ebiznet Corporation SQL Server DBA

October 2000 - October 2001 (1 year 1 month)

Boca Raton - FL - USA

Responsible for the company's database. Functions: Migration from SQL Server 7.0 to SQL Server 2000, creation of databases for the new websites developed by the company, implementation of the backup and restore procedures, data modeling, users creation and maintenance, creation of tables, triggers, stored procedures, functions, views and indexes and help the developers to resolve database problems. Responsible for the company's intranet development. This intranet was developed to control all customers, investors, phone calls, invoices and to help the marketing department in the daily work. This system was developed using Sql Server 2000, ASP, Javascript e Html.

Relacional Consultoria

Oracle Developer

January 1999 - September 2000 (1 year 9 months)

Client : Rio de Janeiro's City Hall Education Department.

Responsible for the development and maintenance of all Oracle related parts in the project, as creating tables, triggers, store procedures, functions, views and indexes using PL/SQL language. Also responsible for store procedures tuning and project documentation using

Oracle Designer.

Client: CGU Insurance Company

Modeled and coded the development of the company's internal Help Desk Application using Oracle Designer and Oracle Forms 4.5. Also monitored CGU's Life Insurance Application using Oracle Forms 4.5 and Oracle Reports 2.5.

### Education

Petropolis Catholic University

Degree in Computer Science · (1990 - 1994)